<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discovery of the ignorance, blindness, and darkness of those who are called magistrates about Carlile in Cumberland, who call Light darkness, and truth error, and judge them blasphemers who are sent of the Lord to declare the eternal word of truth amongst them, but the Lord hath made himself manifest in the hearts of his people, and opened their eyes here in the northern parts, whereby they plainly see the tyranny, oppression, and cruelty of those who are called magistrates and rulers, who do imprison the servants of the most high God, for declaring against sin and abomination, held up in markets and steeple-houses, and so they that depart from iniquity and stand in obedience to the commands of the Lord, makes himself a prey to that generation; but the Lord is risen for Sions deliverance, all praise and glory be to him for evermore. J.C.</title>
            <author>Camm, John, 1604?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E740_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79534)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 114:E740[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discovery of the ignorance, blindness, and darkness of those who are called magistrates about Carlile in Cumberland, who call Light darkness, and truth error, and judge them blasphemers who are sent of the Lord to declare the eternal word of truth amongst them, but the Lord hath made himself manifest in the hearts of his people, and opened their eyes here in the northern parts, whereby they plainly see the tyranny, oppression, and cruelty of those who are called magistrates and rulers, who do imprison the servants of the most high God, for declaring against sin and abomination, held up in markets and steeple-houses, and so they that depart from iniquity and stand in obedience to the commands of the Lord, makes himself a prey to that generation; but the Lord is risen for Sions deliverance, all praise and glory be to him for evermore. J.C.</title>
                  <author>Camm, John, 1604?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.C. = John Camm.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Carlisle --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England --  Carlisle --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True DISCOVERY Of the <hi>Ignorance, Blindneſs, and Darkneſs</hi> Of thoſe Who are called Magiſtrates about <hi>Carlile</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who call Light Darkneſs, and Truth Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and judge them blaſphemers who are ſent of the Lord to declare the eternal word of truth amongſt them, but the Lord hath made himſelf manifeſt in the hearts of his people, and opened their eys here in the northern parts, whereby they plainly ſee the Tyranny, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Cruelty of thoſe who are called Magiſtrates and Rulers, who do impriſon the ſervants of the moſt high God, for declaring againſt ſin and abomination, held up in Markets and Steeple-houſes, and ſo they that depart from iniquity and ſtand in obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Lord, makes himſelf a prey to that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but the Lord is riſen for Sions deliverance, all Praiſe and Glory be to him for evermore. J. C.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>G. Calvert,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:114699:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114699:2"/>
            <head>A true diſcovery of the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Blindneſs, and Darkneſs, of thoſe who are called Magiſtrates about <hi>Carlile</hi> in <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Im whom the world calls <hi>George Fox,</hi> was moved of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, to go into <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and the Lord let him ſee he had a people in it, and was moved to go into <hi>Carlile,</hi> and was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to go into the Market, and ſtept upon the ſide of the Croſs, and a grief came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to ſee the deceits and filthineſs that the people lived in, and he was moved to bid them lay away all deceitful Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, and cozening and cheating, and bad them repent for the judgement day of the Lord is coming, and other words as he paſſed up the ſtreets; afterwards he was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to go up to the Caſtle to ſpeak to the ſouldiers to ſhew them where their Teacher was, and their condemnation was the light of Chriſt that hated it; then upon; the firſt day he was moved to go to the Steeple-houſe, and he ſtayed till the Prieſt had done; and the Prieſt paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away, and then the rude multitude roſe, and there was a cry, Down with the Roundheaded rogues.</p>
            <p>ANd upon the ſecond day of the week, the Magiſtrates thereabouts, they ſent for him the ſaid <hi>George,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined him, and ſent him to priſon, as the examination fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114699:3"/>
            <p>Oh the oaths that is in the Land, the Land mourns becauſe of oaths and fighters, ſtrikers and drunkards, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wickedneſs, ſo that men if they can but have a kinde of a cuſtom of preaching and telling what the Prophets and Apoſtles ſpoke, And to have a fellow to have ſo much in the year to read it and expound it, or preach it as they call it, and people to come once a week to hear him, ſo then after, ſome to the Ale-houſe drinking, and ſome fighting and ſwearing and curſing, when many hath been moved of the Lord to go into their Aſſemblies, and to ſpeak what they have been moved of the Lord to ſpeak in the time of their ſpeaking, ſome ſtriking with Bibles, ſome with fiſts, ſome with ſtones, and ſome haled to the ſtocks and before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and ſo to priſon, and ſay they have broken Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Law, which Law guarded all the Papiſts and Jeſuits, which Law guards the Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> now, ſo then you are under the popiſh act and his power, which is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the unlimited power which power ſhould limit the ſpirit of the mighty God of Heaven and Earth, who is ſetting up his own Law, who will give liberty to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeed, I am moved to warn you to take heed how you make Laws to limit the holy Spirit of God, if you do, God will turn his ſword againſt you, and cut you down.</p>
            <p>A friend of them whom the world calls Quakers, when he was brought before the Rulers and Magiſtrates, they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him what was his name, and he ſaid it was hid from the world, and the world knew it not, and they asked him what his name was, and he ſaid they ſhould never know it, and then he was free to tell them what the world called him, elſe he ſaw their deceit. And he asked whether they ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome ſin as long as they were here upon the Earth, and they ſaid no: ſo then he put them among the Papiſts in the Purgatory after death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114699:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Examination and Accuſation of</hi> Geo. Fox.</head>
            <p>THe Accuſation of <hi>George Fox,</hi> being the name as the world calls him by, late of <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at <hi>Carliſle</hi> the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſaith, as the world ſaith, He was born in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> and that he is in perfect me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory at this time, and that he hath attained to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he hath been in Heaven, and that there is but one Son of God, and that he is riſen and ſpeaketh to us now here, and that he doth not commit ſin, for he that is born of God ſinneth not, neither can he have any remorſe for ſin, he that is born of God neither can he, becauſe he is born of God and the ſeed of God remaineth in him, and that the Saints upon the Earth doth judge the hearts, and that <hi>Thomas Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> did ſin in tempting him, by propounding ſome Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him. And he ſaith, That the Bible is a Decſaration of the word of God, and not the Word, but God is the Word, and that which he ſpeaks is true Scripture, and there is but One, and that which he ſpeaks is Truth and Eternal, you ſhall witneſs it, ſpeaking to <hi>Wilfro Lawſon</hi> and others then preſent. And being demanded why he came into the place, he ſaid he was moved of the Lord of Heaven and Earth to ſpeak to the Conſciences of men, and that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly the words that he did ſpeak did harden <hi>Thomas Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> heart, and that he now ſees the face of God as wel as the faces of them that were preſent at this Examination, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked why he continued. in the meeting-place after he was wiſhed to depart, he ſaid, Whether is it better to obey God or man, by the means to avoid tumuits and diſorder, being demanded likewiſe whether he would ſtay in this place, he ſaith he muſt ſtay lo long as his Fathers Will is: And when I began to declare againſt the deceits of the Prieſts, and how they acted contrary to Chriſt, I heard, Make him a Mittimus. And what I was moved of the Lord to come thither for, where every one might have his Teacher, and that in all Conſciences ſhould witneſs me eternally.</p>
            <p>The Rulers wives were the firſt that perſecuted in the Steeple-houſe, and ſtirred up the rude multitude.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114699:4"/>
            <head>A Priſoner of the Lord at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> and ſtanding accuſed for witneſſing forth that which the Saints witneſſed. And having a cloud of Scriptures to maintain nhe ſame, that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ſimple may ſee that it was the righteous ſeed that ever ſuffered by the unrighteous ſeed of evil doers which ſuffers ſo.</head>
            <div n="1" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>ANd for that I am accuſed for ſaying I was in Heaven, which I have many witneſſes in the Scriptures as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid he was caught up into the third Heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.21. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Whom have I in Heaven but thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. And thou haſt made us ſit together in heavenly places, Behold I looked, and behold a dore was opened in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.1. And the ſeventh Angel ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there was great voices in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. And I ſaw another Angel flye in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpel to preach unto them that dwell upon the earth, ſaying with a loud voice, Fear God and give glory to him, for the hour of his judgements is come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6, 7. And I ſaw another ſign in Heaven great and marvellous, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.6, 7. And after I ſaw theſe things I heard a voice of much people in Heaven ſaying, Hallaluiah ſalvation and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honor, and power unto the Lord our God: now if any come to witneſs this fulfilled, ye impriſon them, and ſo would ye do to <hi>John</hi> if he were here, and ſo be witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelves, that ye are in the ſame generation that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſecuted, for <hi>John</hi> and the Apoſtles was perſecuted with the ſame generation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>Ye accuſe me for confeſſing the Son of God and ſaying, I am the Son of God, as many as received him to them he gave power to become the ſons of God, which were born
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114699:4"/>not of blood nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of man but of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12, 13. and muſt not the ſon which is born of God and not by the will of man ſpeak, Behold what manner of love is this, that we ſhould be called the ſons of God, Therefore the world knoweth us not, becauſe it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him not, and marvel not my brethren if the world hate you, we know that we have paſſed from death to life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the brethren, the world ever hated the ſon of God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1, 2, 13, 14. And we know we are of God, and the whole world lyeth in wickedneſs, and we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding that is true, and we are in him thats true, even in his ſon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, this is the true God and eternal life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19, 20. God called <hi>Iſrael</hi> his ſon, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22. and the ſon of God was an Iſraelite indeed, in whom there was no guile, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. Thou art my ſon this day have I begotten thee. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. unto us a ſon is given, A virgin ſhall bear a ſon and this is my well-beloved Son, in whom I am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, no man knows the Son but the Father, neither knows any man the Father ſave the Son, and him to whomſoever the Son ſhall reveal him, and where he is revealed muſt he not ſpeak, no man hath ſeen God at any time, the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſon which is in the boſom of the Father, he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared him, where this ſon is made manifeſt, declares the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now, which no man can, for he hath not ſeen God, and he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life; and here you have cleared your ſelves from God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>I ſaid I ſaw Gods face: The Lord ſpoke to <hi>Moſes</hi> face to face as a man ſpeaks to his friend, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.11. and might not he confeſs it, now if any confeſs he ſees the face of God you impriſon them, ſhewing ye take counſel againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed. And <hi>Jacob</hi> whoſe name was changed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaw God face to face, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30. And might not he confeſs it where <hi>Iacob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> is riſen ſees the ſame as he ſaw, but <hi>Eſau</hi> doth not, but ſeeks to ſlay <hi>Iacob,</hi> now <hi>Eſau</hi> who was a fornicator and a prophane perſon, who for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114699:5"/>one morſel of meat ſold his birth-right, for the luſt, and all who lives in the luſt, fornication and prophaneneſs are in the ſame nature now, and ſuch are they that perſecutes <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> now which ſees God face to face, and here the Scripture is fulfilled, And <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear, but now my eys ſee thee; and muſt he deny that he ſaw God. Now he who confeſſes he ſees God ye impriſon, ye ſhew your ſelves to be in the generation that ever perſecuted the righteous ſeed in all ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ſeed is Chriſt. Now to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed were the promiſes made, he ſaith not to ſeeds as of many, but to one and to thy ſeed which is Chriſt, as if there be 10000 one ſeed which is Chriſt in all, and muſt not this ſeed ſpeak, or the ſeed of the ſerpent? Whether Chriſt or the Serpent? And if Chriſt be in you the body is dead becauſe of ſin, but the ſpirit is life, becauſe of righteouſneſs; and the pure in heart ſees good. And ye have ſhewed forth your corrupt hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid I did not commit ſin, he that believeth is born of God, whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is born of God, in this the children of God are manifeſt and the children of the devil, for this purpoſe the Son was made manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the devil, where the ſon of God is not made manifeſt, the works of the devil are ſtanding, and he that ſinneth hath not ſeen nor known him, <hi>Cain</hi> was that wicked one which ſlew his brother, and wherefore did he ſlay him, becauſe his works were evil, and his brothers righteous: now thou <hi>Cain</hi> appears againſt the righteous ſeed where it is brought forth, the ſecond birth, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. he that is dead is free from ſin, now if we be dead with Chriſt we ſhall alſo live with him, knowing that the old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſin ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin, being then made free from ſin ye became the ſervants of righteouſneſs, but now being made free from ſin and become ſervants to God, ye have your fruit unto holineſs and the end everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114699:5"/>life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18, 20, 22. ye are circumciſed with the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of ſin of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt, but ye are not in the fleſh but in the ſpirit, if ſo the ſpirit of God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in you, now if any man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his, and if Chriſt be in you the body is dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſin, and muſt not this Chriſt ſpeak where he is made manifeſt, and kill the body of ſin, which Chriſt is but one yeſterday to day and for ever, and is there any Chriſt but this which kills the body of ſin, and Chriſt in you the hope of glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>As the ſame Chriſt as ever was made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples I will come again to you, that your joy may be full, the ſame Chriſt that ſuffered, and when he is come which the Phariſees and Jews will not have to rule and ſpeak, which ruled over the Diſciples and ſpoke to them, and taught them, and when he is come again muſt he not ſpeak? and where he is made manifeſt, and be King and rule; That Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and, if it be any other Chriſt but that Chriſt, he is Antichriſt, for Chriſt is but one in all his Saints, the ſame Chriſt yeſterday to day and for ever. And <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> why perſecuteſt thou me, for it was that Chriſt that was riſen that ſaid he was perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he is the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world, I was in priſon, and I was ſick, and ye viſited me not, hungry and naked and ye clothed me not, but as much as ye did it not to one of theſe little ones ye did it not unto me. And its the ſpirit of your Father that ſpeaketh in you, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye have the ſame ſpirit, that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead ye are none of his. And if you have the ſame ſpirit muſt not that ſpirit ſpeak Chriſt in you the hope of glory, which is the myſtery which is hid from Ages and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but now is made manifeſt the ſame Chriſt as ever was, and muſt not this Chriſt ſpeak where he is made manifeſt, or muſt he be dumb? The ſon of perdition in man which is exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that is called God, he would not have the one Chriſt to regn and ſpeak which is in all his Saints, who is the head
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114699:6"/>of the man, and muſt not the head of the man ſpeak but where the Prince of the Ayr rules, and the Son of perdition above all that is called God, they have a priſon to put Chriſt into where he ſpeaks, who diſobeys the light of Chriſt in them, and impriſons it, they are the hypocrite Phariſees, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and chief Prieſts, which under colour and profeſſion of Chriſt and God, yet they are the enemies to the Son of God and impriſons him thus, where he is made manifeſt, and they that were then againſt Chriſt, they are the ſame againſt him now in Nature, for Chriſt to day yeſterday and for ever, is witneſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid the Bible was not the word of God, God is the Word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. it is but a declaration of the Word, and the word was God, and the word was made fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us, This was not the Letter, and the Letter ſaith the word is ſharper then a two-edged ſword, he doth not ſay the Bible is ſharper then a two-edged ſword, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith the word is as a hammer and a fire, but he doth not ſay the Letter is a hammer and a fire, but the Letter ſaith the Word is ſo, ſo you blaſpheme in ſaying the Bible is the Word, and ſets it up before God who is the Word, and was before the Letter was.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid I had no remorſe for ſin, and that the Saints judged the hearts.</p>
               <p>He that is born of God ſinneth not, what remorſe for ſin can there be in him, which doth not commit ſin, love think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil, ſo it cannot have remorſe for that it thinketh not, and a good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, and as he is ſo are we in this preſent world, and he that doth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.17, 18. Their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more, now where remiſſion is there is no Sacrifice for ſin, and here you ſhew your ſelves ignorant of the Scripture, as you may, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24.25. <hi>Job</hi> 21.27.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaith judge not by outward appearance but with righteous judgement: and the Apoſtle ſaith the Saints ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114699:6"/>judge the world, and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith he hath ſet the work in their hearts, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. they ſet their hearts on iniquity, there he judged their iniquity, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> Judges the heart, 14.13. the Lord let him ſee their hearts, <hi>Stephen</hi> judged their hearts, <hi>Act.</hi> 7. and here you ſhew your ſelves ignorant of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and the life that gave them forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Examination</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>And whereas I ſaid my words hardened <hi>Creſters</hi> heart, which the event of it did ſhew forth, when the Apoſtles did ſpeak of the things concerning the Kingdom of God, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were hardened and believed not, but ſpeak evil of that way, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.8, 9. As you do now, is this Scripture ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and was not <hi>Creſters</hi> and the reſt hardened, <hi>Pharoah</hi>-like, who impriſoned the juſt for telling the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Accuſation</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid I was perfect, <hi>Noah</hi> was perfect in his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. And that ye ſtand perfect and compleat in the will of God, for by one Offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, The Apoſtle ſaid he ſpoke wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom among them that were perfect, as many as are perfect be thus minded, the Apoſtle did not bid impriſon them, now ſee how contrary you walk to Scripture rule, who impriſons him that ſaith he is perfect, if they which gave forth the Scriptures were here, you would impriſom them; and Chriſt ſaith be you perfect as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect, and every one that is perfect muſt be as his Lord, and as he is ſo are we in this preſent world, <hi>Coll.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusations">
               <head>And for ſaying there was but one ſon of God.</head>
               <p>The Son of God is but one in all the Saints male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, Chriſt all in all. And the ſon it is that makes free, and all that is made free by this ſon, and all that hath the Son of God hath life, and all that hath not this Son of God hath not life, and here you ſhew that you are ignorant of the Scriptures and of this Chriſt this Son of God which you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114699:7"/>have long profeſſed in words that makes ſo many Sects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you but, now perſecutes him and impriſons him wher he is manifeſt, why perſecuteſt thou me, ſaith Jeſus? for them that witneſſed Jeſus was brought out of the Jewiſh Synagogues and Temple, and they haled them out and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them as you do no now who witneſſed the ſubſtance. And they muſt come of the Prieſts and witneſſed the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable Prieſthood Chriſt Jeſus, ſo now they who do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the unchangeable Prieſthood, and are brought of the worlds Aſſemblies which hath the form, and to them holds forth the power, ſuch as are haled forth of the Synagogues and impriſoned, with you who have the form as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had.</p>
               <p>And for that which was ſaid, the Son of God ſpake to them there and is riſen. Where the Son of God is made manifeſt muſt he not ſpeak, here you have ſhewed forth your ſelves, he that is born after the fleſh perſecutes him that is born after the Spirit and perſecntes him, and priſons him, and here you yave ſhewed that you priſon the ſon of God, here ſee if your Laws be not your Wills as the Jews was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, and be ye witneſſes againſt your ſelves, know ye not that Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates.</p>
               <p>And as for ſaying <hi>Thomas Creſter</hi> tempted him, did not they who was out of the Truth tempt the ſon of God, who had the form of the Prophets and Holy men of God, conditions but not the life as you have now, the form of Chriſt the Prophets and Apoſtles, for had you had the life of Jeſus Chriſt you would have owned him whom you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, but kept peace, or had you owned the Law of God which was made for ſinners, you would not have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned the juſt who in love for your ſouls good came to declare the Truth to you, whom you put him under a cruel Tyrant Jaylors hand who ſtrook him in priſon when he ſpoke not a word to him.</p>
               <p>And as for ſpeaking to <hi>Willfro Lawſon</hi> and them that was preſent what he ſpoke was true Scripture, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114699:7"/>was but one, it all being given forth by the inſpiration of the Spirit, and the Spirit is but one that gave it forth, and the holy Ghoſt is but one, which the holy men of God was moved to ſpeak it from: now you that have not this Spirit and the holy Ghoſt, perſecute them who are in the one Life, and with the one Spirit, owns it to be one, and ſuch as you perſecute them that witneſs it, as your fathers did, which gave it forth.</p>
               <p>To the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one of you withal I ſpeak which lets you ſee your evil deeds, which you love it, it will bring you to repentance of what you have done, which light will guide your mindes up to God, which if you hate it, you hate God and Chriſt, then this light is your condemnation, and to you this is true Scripture, and the light in your conſcience will witneſs what I ſpeak: for you that hate it, hate me, but it is no marvel, for the world ever hated the ſon of God where he was made manifeſt, as you may read in <hi>John,</hi> there let the Scripture it ſelf judge you.</p>
               <p>And as for ſaying, He was moved of the Lord to ſpeak to that in the conſciences of men, <hi>Holy men of God ſpake as they was moved by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and the Miniſters of God are made manifeſt to that of God in mans conſciences. And here again you have cleared your ſelves from the holy Ghoſt and the Miniſters of the Spirit, which miniſters to the ſpirit in priſon. Oh that ever men ſhould profeſs the Scripture, and perſecute the life where it is made manifeſt! but no other fruit is looked from ſuch trees, but the Lord is coming to hew down all tree that have cumbred the ground, but with the life that gave forth the Scriptures, ſhall you all be judged that act contrary to that in your conſcience: for to that I ſpeak, and that is it which ſhall witneſs me, and condemn you that hate it.</p>
               <p>As for ſaying, It was better to obey God and man: Did not the Apoſtles ask the ſame queſtion when they was brought before Magiſtrates, which witneſſed forth Chriſt: and they was haled out of the Synagogues, and Priſoned, and haled before Magiſtrates: And have not you Magiſtrates
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114699:8"/>ſhewed your ſelves to be in the ſame nature, to priſon and perſecute, and ſlander the innocent: And let all ſee that you have acted contrary to the Scripture, and that your wills would be obeyed, who priſons him that doth obey God, and let the Scripture it ſelf judge you.</p>
               <p>And for asking him, How long he could ſtay in that place? his Anſwer was, As long as his Fathers will was. And there again you do ſhew you are acting contrary to the Scripture and the Apoſtles doctrine who taught the people to ſay, <hi>If God will:</hi> and to ſtand in his will let the Scripture it ſelf judge you. And for ſaying to avoid diſorder where is the power, that is, terror to evil doers, where is the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that keeps in order: Oh for ſhame never profeſs your ſelves to be Magiſtrates, had you heard him ſpoken or acted any thing contrary to the Law, then your Law might have been ſaid upon, but you, but you priſoned him contrary to Law, but only your own wills, ſo the juſt Law of God will take hold upon you, and vengeance is the Lords, and he will repay it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114699:8"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of the preſent practiſe of the Profeſsion in ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>OH <hi>England,</hi> thou that haſt profeſſed the Scripture, that which <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote, the Law, that which the Prophets which was ſent of the Lord ſpake forth; that which <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> preached, which was a burning and ſhining light; that which Chriſt Jeſus, the ſubſtance of all, when he was upon earth, and that that he ſpake after his Reſurrection, and that that the Apoſtles ſpake, which was ſent of him to preach unto all Nations: And thou makes a Profeſſion of what the Apoſtles wrote to the Saints of God, which was come out of the world, and which was not of the world, of whom the end of the world was come: And of them that was come to the General Aſſemblies of the Firſt-born, which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect; all theſe you make a profeſſion of in words, and your Teachers give meanings to them with their carnal mindes of the outward Letter, which was ſpoken from the life: For thoſe that did ſpeak them did poſſeſs and enjoy what they ſpake, but you are ignorant of the life of them; for where the life of them is made manifeſt, them you do perſecute, beat, and ſtock, and hail to priſon, as all your generation of profeſſors of an outward thing ever did, who knew nothing of the inward, O be aſhamed and bluſh, and tremble before the Lord God, who hath ſo long worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the beaſt, and given all your glory and honor to the beaſt, not knowing the living God, nor the firſt principle that leads to life. And that your Leaders and Teachers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the light, which Chriſt Jeſus ſaith he hath enlightned every one that comes into the world with all. And that the power of the Lord which cauſes trembling and quaking, which all the holy men of God that ever heard the voyce of God, which is terrible, which ſhakes the earth, ever wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed while the earth was ſtanding in them. And this you call Impoſtures and Deluſions, and of the Devil, which makes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114699:9"/>manifeſt that you know nothing of God, nor never heard his voyce, nor ſeen his face. Oh woful and miſerable is your condition, which wars againſt the living God, your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is more miſerable then any that ever went before you. You ſay, you have the word of God, and that which you call your word is a Declaration of the eternal Word, which Chriſt and the Apoſtles ſpake forth. Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, there you may be alſo:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>Glorifie thy ſon, that thy ſon alſo may glorifie thee, and as thou haſt given him power over all fleſh, that he may give eternal life to as many as thou haſt given him:</hi> Now if any come to witneſs the Reſurrection of the dead or eternal life, or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Chriſt come again, or the Holy Ghoſt, as the Apoſtles did, or witneſs the Son of God made manifeſt, him you beat, ſtock, ſtone, impriſon, hale before Magiſtrates, perſecute as vagabonds and wanderers, and many ſaith, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kills them, they do God good ſervice; and there the Scripture is fulfilled on you: And ſee now what your faith is, in this you call your word, when you do not believe it, when you ſee it fulfilled; nay, ye are more cruel then the Scribes and Phariſees was, which crucified Jeſus Chriſt; for they looked for a Chriſt, becauſe the Prophets had prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied on him, but when he came they did not know him; but asked him, <hi>If he was the Chriſt:</hi> but now you profeſs Chriſt come in the fleſh, and Chriſts Reſurrection, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, as the Scripture mentions, and you ſay, it is ſo, becauſe the Letter ſaith it is ſo, though you know nothing of the Reſurrection of the dead, but denies the firſt principle, the light that leads to life, and to the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and death reigns in you that hath paſſed over all men, and you are looking without you, ſaying, Lo here is Chriſt, and lo there, contrary to Chriſts Command, and there that propheſie of Chriſt is fulfilled upon you, who ſaith, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven cometh not with obſervations, but the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven is in you; and you are perſecuting them whom Chriſt hath enlightned, and who witneſſes the Scriptures as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114699:9"/>as they ſpeak, who bears teſtimony to the truth of them. And here you are found lyars, and ſayers, but not doers, as the Scribes and Phariſees were that Chriſt cryed wo againſt; and here you are without all example or preſident that ever was ſince the creation, that a people ſhould profeſſe a thing and perſecute and impriſon thoſe that poſſeſſes the ſame that you profeſſe: And here you are above all cruelty and tyranny that ever was, but you are given up to hardneſſe of heart, and blindeneſſe, and your Leaders and Teachers have erred from the Lord, though they have profeſſed the words of Chriſt, where it will make for their own ends and purpoſes; yet they deny the light which Chriſt ſaith he hath enlightned every one with that comes into the world, which is the light of the conſcience, which is in every man, which they ſay is natural; and here they keep people from the firſt principle that leads into truth and into obedience of the Lord. And they deny Revelations, and ſo denies Jeſus Chriſt; though Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That none knows the father but the ſon, and he to whom he doth reveal him;</hi> and ſo you keep poor people ſtrangers from the life of God: and they deny perfection and cleanſing from ſin while they are here; though Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your heavenly father is perfect;</hi> and, <hi>by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified;</hi> and the Scripture witneſſes the cleanſing of the Saints all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, and the perfecting of them according to their growth, but poor people are kept in blindneſs and ignorance, with hearkning to their filthy inventions and blind imaginations and meanings that they give to the Scripture, when no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of it came not by the will of man, but the Lord God of power and life is found true, and all them are found to be lyars, eternal praiſes be unto his name for ever: For Chriſt Jeſus is riſen, and the Son is revealed, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt is witneſſed, which cleanſeth from all ſin. And the Eternal Spirit of Life is witneſſed, which all the blind guides are ignorant of praiſes, praiſes be to the Lord God for ever. Therefore all people every where, if you would know the living God, hearken to the light in your conſciences, which convinceth you, and lets you ſee ſin and evil, and checks you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114699:10"/>when you do wrong, let that lead and guide your mind and that will lead you to God, who is the Father of light, turn your minds within, and keep cloſe to the light in your conſcience, there is your Teacher, and that is it; and if you do not obey it, that will be your eternal condemnation, ſo if you love your ſouls, hearken diligently unto that, and your ſoul ſhall live; and ſpend not your money for that which is not bread, nor go not after your blind Guides, for they know not what the ſoul is, nor where it is, but one ſaith, this is the ſoul; another ſaith, that is the ſoul; nor none of them knows that they have a ſoul, nor cannot witneſs a living ſoul, but they are them that makes merchandize of ſouls. Therefore beware of them, as you love your ſouls and go not after them, now you have time prize it, and if you love the light which Chriſt hath enlightened you withal, you love your ſouls: and if you hate this light which would keep your mindes up to God, you hate your ſouls.</p>
            <p>IF any one in <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> or <hi>Cumberland,</hi> or elſewhere, that owns the truth, have a love to Chriſt, and owns his light which he hath enlightened every one that comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world with all, and hath a love to God; and are not ſatisfied in the things of God, with him whom the world calls <hi>George Fox</hi> hath ſpoken and declared forth, let them declare it, and publiſh it in writing; and not to backbite nor lye, nor perſecute in ſecret, this I demand and command of you all in the preſence of the living God, as you will anſwer it in the preſence of the living God. For the exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the truth, and the confounding of the deceit, is this given forth, that truth may be exalted, and deceit confounded, to that of God in the Conſciences I ſpeak, declare or write it to any of them whom you call Quakers, that truth may be exalted, and all things come to the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one with that comes into the world: and that nothing ſhould be hid in darkneſs, priſons or holes, or corners, that all things may come to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114699:10"/>the light of Chriſt, and tryed with the light of Chriſt: this was I moved of the Lord to write forth, to be ſet on the Croſſes in <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> and elſewhere: To the light of Chriſt in you I ſpeak, that none of you may ſpeak evil of the things of God you know not, leſt you be found fighters againſt God, and the hand of the Lord be turned againſt you, and not to act contrary to the light that gave forth the Scriptures.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
